  <appendix id="feedback">
    <title>Feedback</title>
    <para>This section contains information on reporting bugs in MATE, making suggestions and comments about MATE applications or documentation, and ways in which you can help MATE.</para>
    

    <section id="feedback-bugs">
    <title>Reporting Bugs</title>
    <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: This section is material taken from mate-desktop/desktop-docs/mate-feedback/ Look for existing translations there before translating it all over again :) -->
      <para>
     If you have found a bug in a MATE application, please
   report it! Developers do read all the bug reports and try to fix
   these bugs. Please try to be as specific as possible when
   describing the circumstances under which the bug shows (what
   commands did you enter? which buttons did you click?). If there were any
   error messages, be sure to include them, too.  
      </para> 
      <para>
	The easiest way to report bugs is by using <application>Bug Buddy</application>, MATE's built-in bug reporting tool. This will launch automatically in the event that an application crashes. The details MATE developers need are automatically collected, but you can further help by giving information about what you were doing when the crash took place.
      </para>
      <para>
	You can also submit bugs and browse the list of known bugs by
	connecting to the <ulink type="http"
	url="https://github.com/mate-desktop/">MATE bug tracking
	database</ulink>.  You will need to register before you can
	submit any bugs this way. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Please note that some of MATE applications are developed outside of MATE, or by
	commercial companies (these products are still free
	software). For example, <application>blueman</application>, a
	bluetooth application, is developed at <ulink type="http"
    url="https://github.com/blueman-project/blueman/">GitHub</ulink>. Bugs reports and
	comments about these products should be directed to the
	respective organization or company. If you are using <application>Bug 
	Buddy</application>, it will automatically send bug reports to
	the correct database.
	</para>


    </section>
    <section id="feedback-wishlist"> 
      <title>Suggestions and Comments</title> 
      <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: This section is material taken from mate-desktop/desktop-docs/mate-feedback/ Look for existing translations there before translating it all over again :) -->      
      <para> 
	If you have a suggestion or want to request a new feature for
      one of the applications, it can also be done using the bug
      tracking database. Submit your suggestion as a bug report as
      described in <xref linkend="feedback-bugs" /> and at the appropriate
      step select <guilabel>Severity: Enhancement</guilabel>. 
      </para>
    </section>

      <section id="feedback-docs">
      <title>Documentation Comments</title>
      <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: This section is material taken from mate-desktop/desktop-docs/mate-feedback/ Look for existing translations there before translating it all over again :) -->      

      <para> If you found an inaccuracy or misprint in one of MATE
	documents, or have any comments or suggestions about
	documentation, please let us know! The easiest way of doing so
	is by submitting a bug report as explained before and
	selecting <guilabel>Component: docs</guilabel> at appropriate
	steps (or <guilabel>general</guilabel> if there is no
	<guilabel>docs</guilabel> component). If your comment is about
	general MATE documentation (such as <citetitle>MATE Users
	Guide</citetitle>) rather than specific application manual,
	select <guilabel>Product: mate-user-docs</guilabel>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Alternatively, you can just send your comments by email to the
	<ulink type="http"
	url="http://ml.mate-desktop.org/listinfo">MATE
	Documentation Project</ulink> mailing list.
      </para>
    </section>
    <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: end of old material -->


    <section id="joinmate">
      <title>Joining the MATE Project</title>
      <para>We hope you enjoy using MATE and that you find working with MATE productive. However, there is always room for improvement.</para>
      <para>MATE invites you to join our free software community if you have some spare time. There are many different fields. MATE needs programmers, but it also needs translators, documentation writers, testers, artists, writers, and more.</para>
      <para>For more information on joining MATE, please visit <ulink type="http" url="http://live.gnome.org/JoinMate">http://live.gnome.org/JoinMate</ulink>.</para>
      <para>For more information on giving feedback on MATE, such as bug reports, suggestions, and corrections to documentation, see <xref linkend="feedback-bugs" />.</para>

    </section>
  

  </appendix>
