<!-- -*- indent-tabs-mode: nil -*- -->
<chapter id="overview">
<title>Desktop Overview</title>

<!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
<anchor id="gosoverview-1"/>

<!-- MOVE THESE ANCHORS -->
<!-- Desktop Overview / To Find Out More -->
<anchor id="gosoverview-12"/>
<!-- Desktop Overview / To Find Out More / About MATE Desktop Topics -->
<anchor id="gosoverview-31"/>
<!-- Desktop Overview / To Find Out More / About Applets -->
<anchor id="gosgetstarted-33"/>
<!-- Desktop Overview / To Find Out More / About Applications -->
<anchor id="gosgetstarted-35"/>


<highlights>
  <para>This chapter introduces you to some of the very basic components of the desktop. These components include <glossterm>Windows</glossterm>, <glossterm>Workspaces</glossterm>, and <glossterm>Applications</glossterm>. Almost all the work (or play) that you do in MATE will involve these very basic components.</para>
  
  <note>
  <para>This chapter describes the default configuration of MATE.
  Your vendor or system administrator may have configured your
  desktop to look different than what is described here.</para>
  </note>
</highlights>

<section id="overview-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
  <anchor id="gosoverview-5"/>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>MATE Desktop components, introducing</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>When you start a desktop session for the first time,
  you should see a default startup screen, with panels, windows,
  and various icons.</para>
  
  <para>The major components of the MATE Desktop are as follows:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Desktop</term>
      <listitem><para>The desktop itself is behind all of the other components on the
      desktop.  You can place objects on the desktop to access your files and
      directories quickly, or to start applications that you use often.  See
      <xref linkend="overview-desktop"/> for more information.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>  
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Panels</term>
      <listitem><para>The <firstterm>panels</firstterm> are the two bars that run along the top and bottom of the screen. By default, the top panel shows you the MATE main menu bar, the date and time, and a set of application launcher icons, and the bottom panel shows you the list of open windows and the workspace switcher.</para>
      <para>Panels can be customized to contain a variety of tools, such as other menus and launchers, and small utility applications, called
      <firstterm>panel applets</firstterm>. For example, you can configure
      your panel to display the current weather for your location.  For more
      information on panels, see <xref linkend="panels"/>.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Windows</term>
      <listitem><para>Most applications run inside of one or more windows.
      You can display multiple windows on your desktop at the same time.
      Windows can be resized and moved around to accommodate your workflow.
      Each window has a <firstterm>titlebar</firstterm> at the top with
      buttons which allow you to minimize, maximize, and close the window.
      For more information on working with windows, see
      <xref linkend="overview-windows"/>.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Workspaces</term>
      <listitem><para>You can subdivide your desktop into separate
      <firstterm>workspaces</firstterm>.  Each workspace can contain
      several windows, allowing you to group related tasks together.
      For more information on working with workspaces, see
      <xref linkend="overview-workspaces"/>.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>File Manager</term>
      <listitem><para>The <application>Caja</application> file manager
      provides access to your files, folders, and applications.  You can
      manage the contents of folders in the file manager and open the files
      in the appropriate applications.  See <xref linkend="caja"/> for
      more information.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Control Center</term>
      <listitem><para>You can customize your computer using the 
      <application>Control Center</application>, which can be found in the 
      <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu on the top panel menubar. 
      Each preference tool in the Control Center allows you to change
      a particular part of the behavior of your computer. See 
      <xref linkend="prefs"/> for more information on the 
      Control Center.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>Your vendor or system administrator can make configuration changes to
  suit your needs, so your desktop might not match exactly what is described
  in this manual.  Nevertheless, this manual provides a useful introduction
  to using the various components of your desktop.</para>
</section>

<section id="overview-desktop">
  <title>The Desktop</title>
  <anchor id="caja-desktop"/>
  
  <para>The desktop lies behind all other components on your screen. When no windows are visible, the desktop is that part of the screen between the top and bottom panels. You can place files and folders on the desktop that you want to have easy access to.</para>
  <para>The desktop also has several special objects on it:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>The <interface>Computer</interface> icon gives you access to CDs, removable media such as floppy disks, and also the entire filesystem (also known as the root filesystem). By default, you do not have the security permissions to read other users' files or edit system files, but you may need to do so something such as configure a web server on the computer.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Your Home Folder, labelled <interface><replaceable>username</replaceable>'s Home</interface><!-- translators, change this example as required for your locale -->, where all of your personal files are kept. You can also open this folder from the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> menu.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>The <interface>Trash</interface> is a special folder in which to place files and folders you no longer need. For more on this, see <xref linkend="caja-trash"/>.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>When you insert a CD, a flash drive, or other removable media, or a device containing files such as a music player or a digital camera, an icon representing this device will appear on the desktop.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>As you work with your computer, the desktop becomes obscured by the windows you are working with. To quickly reveal the desktop by minimizing all windows, you can do one of the following:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Click on the <guibutton>Show Desktop</guibutton> button at the far left of the <link linkend="bottom-panel">bottom panel</link>.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo>.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
 
    <para>Either action will also restore your windows to their previous state. Alternatively, you can switch to another workspace to see the desktop.</para>
    
    <para>You can change the colour of the desktop background or the image displayed there. For more on this, see <xref linkend="prefs-desktopbackground"/>.</para>

    <note><para>The files and folders you put on the desktop are stored in a special folder within your Home Folder, called <filename>Desktop</filename>. Like any other folder, you can put files and other folders directly into it. The only difference is that anything placed into the Desktop folder will then show up on desktop itself.</para></note>
  
</section>

<section id="overview-windows">
  <title>Windows</title>

  <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
  <anchor id="gosoverview-18"/>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>windows</primary>
    <secondary>overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>A <firstterm>window</firstterm> is a rectangular area of the screen, usually with a border all around and a title bar at the top. You can think of a window as a screen within the screen. Each window displays an application, allowing you to have more than one application visible, and work on more than one task at a time. You can also think of windows as pieces of paper on your desktop: they can overlap, or be side by side, for example.</para>
  
  <para>You can control a window's position of the screen, as well as its size. You can control which windows overlap other windows, so the one you want to work with is completely visible. For more about moving and resizing windows, see <xref linkend="windows-manipulating"/>.</para>
  
  <para>Each window is not necessarily a different application. An application usually has one main window, and may open additional windows at the request of the user.</para>

  <para>The rest of this section describes the different types of windows and how you
  can interact with them.</para>

  <section id="windows-types">
    <title>Types of Windows</title>

    <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
    <anchor id="gosoverview-16"/>

    <para>There are two main types of window:</para>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Application windows</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Application windows allow all the minimize, 
            maximize and close operations through the buttons on the titlebar. 
            When opening an application you will usually see a 
            window of this type appear.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dialog windows</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Dialog windows appear at the request of an application window. A dialog window may alert you to a problem, ask for confirmation of an action, or request input from you.</para>
            
            <para>For example, if you tell an application to save a document, a dialog will ask you where you want to save the new file. If you tell an application to quit while it is still busy, it may ask you to confirm that you want it to abandon work in progress.</para>
            
            <para>Some dialogs do not allow you to interact with the main application window until you have closed them: these are called <firstterm>modal</firstterm> dialogs. Others can be left open while you work with the main application window: these are called <firstterm>transient</firstterm> dialogs.</para>
            
            <tip><para>You can select the text in a dialog with the mouse. This allows you to copy it to the clipboard (by right-clicking the text and selecting <guilabel>Copy</guilabel>), and paste it into another application. This is useful if you wish to quote the text you see in a dialog when requesting support on the Internet.</para></tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="windows-manipulating">

    <title>Manipulating Windows</title>

    <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
    <anchor id="gosoverview-32"/>

    <para>You can change the size and position of windows on the screen. This allows you to see more than one application and do different tasks at the same time. For example, you might want to read text on a web page while writing with a word processor, or to change to another application to do a different task or check its progress.</para> 
    
    <para>You can <firstterm>minimize</firstterm> a window if you are not currently interested in seeing it. This hides it from view. You can <firstterm>maximise</firstterm> a window to fill the whole screen so you can give it your full attention.</para> 
    
    <para><anchor id="gosoverview-FIG-33"/>Most of these actions are carried out by using the mouse on different parts of the the window's frame (see <xref linkend="mouse-actions"/> for a recap of using the mouse). The top edge of the window frame, called the <firstterm>titlebar</firstterm> because it also displays the title of the window, contains several buttons that change the way the window is displayed.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="fig-titlebar-anno-window"/> shows the titlebar for a typical application window. From left to right, this contains the Window Menu button, the window title, the minimize button, the maximize button, and the close button.</para>
    
    <figure id="fig-titlebar-anno-window">
      <title>Titlebar for a Typical Application Window</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/titlebar_window.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Titlebar of application window frame.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>All actions can also be carried out from the Window Menu. To open this, click on the Window Menu button at the left-hand edge of the titlebar. Common actions can also be carried out with keyboard shortcuts: see <xref linkend="shortcuts-window"/> for a simple list of these. The following lists the actions you can carry out on a window, with the mouse or the keyboard:</para>

   <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Move the window</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Drag the titlebar to move the window. You can click on any part of the titlebar except the buttons at either end to begin the drag action. The window will move on the screen as you drag the mouse. On less powerful computers, the movement of the window may be represented by moving an outline of its frame.</para>
            
            <para>You can also choose Move from the Window Menu, or press <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo>, and then either move the mouse or press the keyboard arrow keys to move the window.</para>
            
            <para>You can also press-and-hold <keycap>Alt</keycap> and drag any part of the window.</para>            
            
            <para>As you move the window, some parts of the screen will give slight resistance to movement. This is to help you align windows more easily to the edges of the desktop, the panels, and the edges of other windows.</para>
            
            <para>You can also press-and-hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> while you move the window to cause it to only move between the corners of the desktop and other windows.</para>
            
           <tip><para>If the <keycap>Num Lock</keycap> key is off, you can use the arrows on the numeric keypad, as well as the <keycap>7</keycap>, <keycap>9</keycap>, <keycap>1</keycap>, and <keycap>3</keycap> keys to move diagonally.</para></tip>            
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Resize the window</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Drag one of the borders to expand or contract the window on that side. Drag a corner to change two sides at once. The <link linkend="mouse-pointers">resize pointer</link> appears when your mouse is in the correct position to begin the drag action.</para>

            <para>You can also choose Resize from the Window Menu, or press <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F8</keycap></keycombo>. The resize pointer appears. Move the mouse in the direction of the edge you want to resize, or press one of the keyboard arrows keys. The pointer changes to indicate the chosen edge. Now you can use the mouse or the arrow keys to move this edge of the window. Click the mouse or press <keycap>Return</keycap> to accept the change. Press <keycap>Escape</keycap> to cancel the resize action and return the window to its original size and shape.</para> 
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Minimize the window</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Click on the Minimize button in the titlebar, the leftmost of the group of three on the right. This removes the window from view. The window can be restored to its previous position and size on the screen from the <firstterm>window list</firstterm> on the <link linkend="gospanel-3">bottom edge panel</link> or the <firstterm>window selector</firstterm> in the top panel.</para>
            
            <para>You can also choose Minimize from the Window Menu, or press <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F9</keycap>
            </keycombo>.</para>  
            
            <tip>
            <para>A minimized window is shown in the window list and the window selector
            with [ ] around its title.</para>
            </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maximize the window</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Click on the Maximize button in the titlebar, the middle of the group of three on the right. This expands the window so it fills the screen (the panels remain visible).</para>
            <para>You can also choose Maximize from the Window Menu, or press <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>, or double-click any part of the titlebar except the buttons at either end.</para>

            <tip>
            <para>If you prefer, you can assign the double-click action to <firstterm>roll up</firstterm> the window: see <xref linkend="prefs-windows"/>.</para>
            </tip>            
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>    
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unmaximize the window</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>When a window is maximized, click again on the Maximize button to restore it to its previous position and size on the screen.</para>

            <para>You can also choose Unmaximize from the Window Menu, press <keycombo>
            <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F5</keycap></keycombo>, or double-click any part of the titlebar except the buttons at either end.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>          
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Close the window</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Click the Close button, the rightmost of the group of three on the right. Closing the window may also close the application itself. The application will ask you to confirm closing a window that contains unsaved work.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>                        
    </variablelist> 
       
    <remark>Workspaces commands or a link to them still to go in this section, perhaps</remark>

  </section>

    <section id="windows-focus">
      <title>Giving Focus to a Window</title>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor id="gosoverview-20"/>       
      <para>To work with an application, you need to give the <firstterm>focus</firstterm> to its window. When a window has focus, any actions such as mouse clicks, typing text, or keyboard shortcuts, are directed to the application in that window. Only one window can have focus at a time. The window that has focus will appear on top of other windows, so nothing covers any part of it. It may also have a different appearance from other windows, depending on your choice of <xref linkend="prefs-theme"/>.</para>
      <para>You can give the focus to a window in any of the following ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          With the mouse, click on any part of the window, if the window is visible.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          On the bottom panel, click on the <guibutton>window list button</guibutton> that represents the window in the <application>Window List</application>.
          </para>
        </listitem>        
        <listitem>
          <para>
          On the top panel, click the <guibutton>window list icon</guibutton> and choose the window you want to switch to from the list. The <guibutton>window list icon</guibutton> is at the extreme right of the panel, and its icon matches that of the current window's <guibutton>Window Menu button</guibutton>.
          </para>
          <note><para>
            If the window you choose is on a different workspace, you will be switched to that workspace. For more on workspaces, see <xref linkend="overview-workspaces"/>.
          </para></note>
          </listitem>    
        <listitem>
          <para>
          With the keyboard, hold the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key and press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key. A pop-up window appears with a list of icons representing each window. While still holding <keycap>Alt</keycap>, press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move the selection along the list: a black rectangle frames the selected icon and the position of the window it corresponds to is highlighted with a black border. When the window you want to see is selected, release the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key. Using <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> instead of just <keycap>Tab</keycap> cycles through the icons in reverse order.      
          </para>
          <note><para>
            You can customize the shortcut used to perform this action with the <link linkend="prefs-keyboard-shortcuts">Keyboard Shortcuts preference tool</link>.
          </para></note>
        </listitem>      
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="overview-workspaces">
    <title>Workspaces</title>

    <!-- Maintained for 2.8 compatibility -->
    <anchor id="gosoverview-39"/>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>workspaces</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Workspaces allow you to manage which windows are on your screen. You can imagine workspaces as being virtual screens, which you can switch between at any time. Every workspace contains the same desktop, the same panels, and the same menus. However, you can run different applications, and open different windows in each workspace. The applications in each workspace will remain there when you switch to other workspaces.</para>

    <para>By default, four workspaces are available. You can switch between them with the <application>Workspace Switcher</application> applet at the right of the <link linkend="bottom-panel">bottom panel</link>. This shows a representation of your workspaces, by default a row of four rectangles. Click on one to switch to that workspace. In <xref linkend="gosoverview-FIG-42"/>, <application>Workspace Switcher</application> contains four workspaces. The first three workspaces contain open windows. The last workspace does not contain currently open windows. The currently active workspace is highlighted.</para>
    
    <figure id="gosoverview-FIG-42">
      <title>Workspaces Displayed in Workspace Switcher</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/workspace_switcher_applet.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Workspace Switcher. The context describes the graphic.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>    
    
     <para>Each workspace can have any number of applications open in it. The number of workspaces can be customized: see <xref linkend="workspace-add"/>.</para>
     
     <tip><para>Workspaces enable you to organize the MATE Desktop when you run many
applications at the same time. One way to use workspaces is to allocate a specific function to each workspace: one for email, one for web browsing, one for graphic design, etc. However, everyone has their own preference and you are in no way restricted to only using workspaces like this.</para></tip>
    
    <section id="gosoverview-41">
      <title>Switching Between Workspaces</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>workspaces</primary>
        <secondary>switching between</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>You can switch between workspaces in any of the following ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the <application>Workspace Switcher</application> applet in the bottom panel, click on the workspace where you want to work.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move the mouse pointer over the <application>Workspace Switcher</application> applet in the bottom panel, and scroll the mouse wheel.</para>
        </listitem>        
        <listitem>
          <para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>right arrow</keycap></keycombo> to switch to the workspace on the right of the current
workspace.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>left arrow</keycap></keycombo> to switch to the workspace on the left of the current
workspace.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <note><para>The arrow shortcut keys work according to how your workspaces are set out in the <application>Workspace Switcher</application> applet. If you change your panel so workspaces are displayed vertically instead of horizontally, use <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>up arrow</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>down arrow</keycap></keycombo> to switch workspaces.</para></note>
    </section>
    <section id="workspace-add">
      <title>Adding Workspaces</title>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor id="gosoverview-40"/>         
      <indexterm>
        <primary>workspaces</primary>
        <secondary>specifying number of</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>To add workspaces to the MATE Desktop, right-click on the <application>Workspace Switcher</application> applet, then choose <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>. The <guilabel>Workspace Switcher Preferences</guilabel> dialog
is displayed. Use the <guilabel>Number of workspaces</guilabel> spin box to
specify the number of workspaces that you require.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="overview-applications">
    <title>Applications</title>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor id="gosoverview-54"/>       
    <indexterm>
      <primary>applications</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
   
    <para>An <firstterm>application</firstterm> is a type of computer program that allows you to perform a particular task. You might use applications to create text documents such as letters or reports; to work with spreadsheets; to listen to your favorite music; to navigate the Internet; or to create, edit, or view images and videos. For each of these tasks, you would use a different application.</para>
    
    <para>To launch an application, open the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu and choose the application you want from the submenus. For more on this, see <xref linkend="applications-menu"/>.</para>
       
    <para>The applications that are part of MATE include the following:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="help:pluma"><application>Pluma Text Editor</application></ulink> can read, create, or modify any kind of simple text without any formatting.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="help:mate-dictionary"><application>Dictionary</application></ulink> allows you to look up definitions of a word. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="help:eom"><application>Image Viewer</application></ulink> can display single image files, as well as large image collections.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="help:gucharmap"><application>Character Map</application></ulink> lets you choose letters and symbols from the <firstterm>Unicode</firstterm> character set and paste them into any application. If you are writing in several languages, not all of the characters you need will be on your keyboard.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><link linkend="caja"><application>Caja File Manager</application></link> displays your folders and their contents. Use this to copy, move and classify your files, and to access CDs, USB flash drives, and any other removable media. When you choose an item from the <link linkend="places-menu"><guimenu>Places</guimenu> menu</link>, a <application>Caja File Manager</application> window opens showing that location.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="help:mate-terminal"><application>Terminal</application></ulink> gives you access to the system command line.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Further standard MATE applications include games, music and video players, a web browser, software accessibility tools, and utilities to manage your system. Your distributor or vendor may have added other applications, such as a word processor and a graphics editor. They may also provide you with a way to install further applications.</para>
    
    <para>All MATE applications have many features in common, which makes it easier to learn how to work with a new MATE application. The rest of this section describes some of these features.</para>

    <section id="overview-lookandfeel">
      <title>Common Features</title>
    
      <para>The applications that are provided with the MATE Desktop
  share many common features, such as similar open and save dialogs and similar-looking icons. This is because they have all been developed using the MATE development platform. An application developed using this platform is called a <firstterm>MATE-compliant application</firstterm>. For example, <application>Caja</application> and the <application>pluma</application> text editor are MATE-compliant applications.</para>
      <para>Some of the features of MATE-compliant applications are as follows:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Consistent look-and-feel</para>
          <para>MATE-compliant applications have a consistent look-and-feel. You can use the <link linkend="prefs-theme"><application>Appearance</application> preference tool</link> to change the look-and-feel of your MATE-compliant applications.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Menubars, toolbars, and statusbars</para>
          <para>Most MATE-compliant applications have a menubar, a toolbar, and a statusbar.
  The menubars usually have a similar structure; for example, the <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu always
  contains an <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
          <para>A <firstterm>toolbar</firstterm> is a bar that appears under the menubar.
  A toolbar contains buttons for the most commonly-used commands. A <firstterm>statusbar</firstterm> is a bar at the bottom of a window that provides information about the current state of what you are viewing in the window. Applications might also contains other bars. For example, <application>Caja</application> contains a location bar.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Default shortcut keys</para>
          <para>MATE-compliant applications use the same shortcut keys to perform the
  same actions. See <xref linkend="keyboard-skills"/> for a list of common shortcut keys.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Drag-and-drop</para>
          <para>When you drag-and-drop something into a MATE-compliant application, 
          it will recognize the format of the items that you dragged and will handle 
          them in an appropriate manner. For example, when you drag a HTML file
  from a <application>Caja</application> window to a web browser, the file
  is displayed in HTML format in the browser. However, when you drag the HTML
  file to a text editor, the file is displayed in plain text format in the text
  editor. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="overview-files">
      <title>Working With Files</title>
      <para>The work you do with an application is stored in <firstterm>files</firstterm>. These may be on your computer's hard drive, or on a removable device such as a USB flash drive. You <firstterm>open</firstterm>  a file to examine it or work on it, and you <firstterm>save</firstterm> a file to store your work. When you are done working with a file, you <firstterm>close</firstterm> it.</para>
      <para>All MATE applications use the same dialogs for opening and saving files, presenting you with a consistent interface. The following sections cover the open and the save dialog in detail.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="filechooser-open">
      <title>Choosing a File to Open</title>
      <para>The <guilabel>Open File</guilabel> dialog allows you to choose a file to open in an application.</para>
      <para>The right-hand pane of the dialog lists files and folders in the current location. You can use the mouse or the arrow keys on your keyboard to select a file.</para>
      <para>Once a file is selected in the list, perform one of the following actions to open it:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Press <keycap>Return</keycap>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Press <keycap>Spacebar</keycap>.</para></listitem>        
        <listitem><para>Double-click the file.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>      
      <para>If you open a folder or a location instead of a file, the <guilabel>Open File</guilabel> dialog updates to show the contents of that folder or location.</para>
      
      <para>To change the location shown in the right-hand pane, do one of the following:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>Open a folder that is listed in the current location.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Open an item in the left-hand pane. This pane lists places such as your Documents folder, your Home Folder, media such as CDs and flash drives, places on your network, and your <link linkend="caja-bookmarks">bookmarks</link>.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Click one of the buttons in the path bar above the file listing pane. This shows the hierarchy of folders that contain your current location. Use the arrow buttons to either side of the button bar if the list of folders is too long to fit.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>The lower part of the <guilabel>Open File</guilabel> dialog may contain further options specific to the current application.</para>
              
      <section id="filechooser-open-filter">
        <title>Filtering the File List</title>
        <para>You can restrict the file list to show only files of certain types. To do this, choose a file type from the drop-down list beneath the file list pane. The list of file types depends on the application you are currently using. For example, a graphics application will list different image file formats, and a text editor will list different types of text file.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="filechooser-open-find">
        <title>Find-as-you-type</title>
          <para>If you know the name of the file you want to open, begin typing it: the file list will jump to show you files whose names begin with the characters you type. Arrow keys will now select from only these files. The characters you have typed appear in a pop-up window at the base of the file list.</para>
          <para>To cancel find-as-you-type, press <keycap>Esc</keycap>.</para>    
      </section>
      
      <section id="filechooser-open-folder">
        <title>Choosing a folder</title> 
        <para>You might sometimes need to choose a folder to work with rather than open a file. For example, if you use <ulink type="help" url="help:engrampa"><application>Archive Manager</application></ulink> to extract files from an archive, you need to choose a folder to place the files into. In this case, the files in the current location are greyed out, and pressing <guibutton>Open</guibutton> when a folder is selected will choose that folder.</para>
      </section>      
           
      <section id="filechooser-open-location">
        <title>Open Location</title>
        <para>You can type a full or relative path to the file you want to open. Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> or click the button at the top left of the window to show (or hide) the <guilabel>Location</guilabel> field. Alternatively, begin typing a full path starting with <filename>/</filename> to show the <guilabel>Location</guilabel> field.</para>
        <para>Type a path from the current location, or an absolute path beginning with <filename>/</filename> or <filename>~/</filename>. The <guilabel>Location</guilabel> field has the following features to simplify the typing of a full filename:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem><para>A drop-down of possible file and folder names is displayed once you begin typing. Use <keycap>down arrow</keycap> and <keycap>up arrow</keycap> and <keycap>Return</keycap> to choose from the list.</para></listitem>
	        <listitem><para>If the part of the name typed uniquely identifies a file or folder, the name is auto-completed. Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to accept the suggested text. For example, if you type "Do", and the only object in the folder beginning with "Do" is <filename>Documents</filename>, then the entire name appears in the field.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      
      <section id="filechooser-open-remote">
        <title>Opening Remote Locations</title>
        <para>You can open files in remote locations by choosing the location from the left panel, or by typing a path to a remote location into the <guilabel>Location</guilabel> field.</para>
        <para>If you require a password to access the remote location, you will be asked for it when you open it.</para>
      </section> 
                   
      <section id="filechooser-open-bookmarks">
        <title>Adding and Removing Bookmarks</title>
        <para>To add the current location to the bookmarks list, press <guibutton>Add</guibutton>, or right-click a folder in the file list and choose <guimenuitem>Add to Bookmarks</guimenuitem>. You can add any folder that is listed in the current location by dragging it to the bookmarks list.</para>
        <para>To remove a bookmark from the list, select it and press <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>.</para>
        <note><para>Changes you make to the bookmarks list also affect the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> menu. For more on bookmarks, see <xref linkend="caja-bookmarks"/>.</para></note>
      </section>      
      <section id="filechooser-open-hidden">
        <title>Showing hidden files</title>
          <para>To show hidden files in the file list, right-click in the file list and choose <guimenuitem>Show Hidden Files</guimenuitem>. For more on hidden files, see <xref linkend="caja-managing-hidden-files"/>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="filechooser-save">
      <title>Saving a File</title>
        <para>The first time you save your work in an application, the <guilabel>Save As</guilabel> dialog will ask you for a location and name for the new file. When you save the file on subsequent occasions it will be updated immediately and you will not be asked to re-enter a location or name for the file. To save to a new file, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
        <para>You can enter a filename and choose a location to save in from the drop-down list of bookmarks and commonly-used locations.</para>
                          
        <section id="filechooser-save-expanded">
          <title>Saving in another location</title>
          <para>To save the file in a location not listed in the drop-down list, click the <guilabel>Browse for other folders</guilabel> expansion label. This shows a file browser similar to the one in the <guilabel>Open File</guilabel> dialog.</para>
          <tip><para>The expanded <guilabel>Save File</guilabel> dialog has the same features as the <link linkend="filechooser-open"><guilabel>Open File</guilabel> dialog</link>, such as filtering, find-as-you-type, and adding and removing bookmarks.</para></tip>
        </section>   
        
        <section id="filechooser-save-overwrite">
          <title>Replacing an existing file</title>
          <para>If you type in the name of an existing file, you will be asked whether you wish to replace the existing file with your current work. You can also do this by choosing the file you want to overwrite in the browser.</para>
        </section>         
               
        <section id="filechooser-save-path">
          <title>Typing a Path</title>
          <para>To specify a path to save a file, type it into the <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field. A drop-down of possible file and folder names is displayed once you begin typing. Use <keycap>down arrow</keycap> and <keycap>up arrow</keycap> and <keycap>Return</keycap> to choose from the list. If only one file or folder matches the partial name you have typed, press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to complete the name.</para>       
        </section>
        
        <section id="filechooser-save-newfolder">
          <title>Creating a New Folder</title>
          <para>If you would like to create a new folder to save your file in, press the <guibutton>Create Folder</guibutton> button. Type a name for the new folder and press <keycap>Return</keycap>. You can then choose to save your file in the new folder, as you would with any other folder.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
